A Guide to the Home for Needy Confederate Women Records, 1862-1997
Library of Virginia
- V. Property files, 1900-1989 (Box 41-43)
  - General Assembly. Revision of deed, 1977 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Memorial Building and Endowment Fund, 1928 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous property agreements (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Raab and Co. Real Estate (5 and 7 E. Grace Street), 1933 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Radford, Va., property, 1970-1971 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Real estate ledger, 1929-1940 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Real estate tax bills (Box 43, Folder 8-9)
  - Sale of Hampstead property, 1939-1940 (Box 43, Folder 10)
- VI. Medical files, 1963-1989 (Box 44-50)
  Medical files include general infirmary records, summarizing routine bed-checks, medication dosages, monitoring of vital signs, and other daily concerns, as well as individual patient files.
  - Infirmary. Bedside charts, December 1966 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, April-October 1963 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, October-December 1963 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, April-October 1964 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, October 1964-March 1965 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, March-September 1965 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, September 1965-February 1966 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, February-June 1966 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, June-September 1966 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, September 1966-January 1967 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, January-April 1967 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, April-July 1967 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, July-October 1967 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, October-November 1967 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, November 1967-January 1968 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, January-March 1968 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, February-July 1968 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, March-April 1968 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, April-June 1968 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, June-August 1968 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, August 1968-February 1969 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, August-October 1968 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, October-November 1968 (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, November-December 1968 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, December 1968-February 1969 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, February-March 1969 (Box 47, Folder 1-2)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, March-May 1969 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, March-July 1969 (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Infirmary. Day and night order books, May-July 1969 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Infirmary. Memos to nursing staff, 1983, 1985-1989 (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Patient files. Anderson, Ann K. (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Patient files. Attkisson, Lorela (Box 47, Folder 8-9)
  - Patient files. Ayres, Jessie F. (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Patient files. Ball, Rosa L. (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Patient files. Bell, Chellie (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Patient files. Boschen, Virginia B. (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Patient files. Bowles, Lena (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Patient files. Butler, Daisy (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Patient files. Campbell, Katie V. (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Patient files. Carr, Ada (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Patient files. Carter, Lorrell S. (Box 48, Folder 9-10)
  - Patient files. Chase, Sadie (Box 48, Folder 11)
  - Patient files. Crump, Mary C. Polly (Box 48, Folder 12)
  - Patient files. Crump, Pearl T. (Box 48, Folder 13)
  - Patient files. Dabney, Jessica F. (Box 48, Folder 14)
  - Patient files. Dixon, Carrie (Box 48, Folder 15)
  - Patient files. Drake, Florence (Box 48, Folder 16)
  - Patient files. Dunnavant, Twonette (Box 48, Folder 17)
  - Patient files. Ely, Ruby J. (Box 48, Folder 18)
  - Patient files. Estes, Aubrey (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Patient files. Fowlkes, Allie (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Patient files. Freeman, Lillie (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Patient files. Gay, Alice (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Patient files. Givens, Grace E. (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Patient files. Harris, Catherine (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Patient files. Hodges, Rebecca (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Patient files. Jordan, Lucille (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Patient files. Joseph, Marian B. (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - Patient files. Kibler, Annie (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - Patient files. Lee, Ora (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Patient files. Lipscomb, Eloise (Home superintendant) (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - Patient files. Long, Vera (Box 49, Folder 13)
  - Patient files. Lowery, Josephine (Box 49, Folder 14)
  - Patient files. Newbill, Etta (Box 49, Folder 15)
  - Patient files. Owen, Virginia (Box 49, Folder 16)
  - Patient files. Payne, Dora (Box 49, Folder 17)
  - Patient files. Patterson, Byrd (Box 49, Folder 18)
  - Patient files. Perlicheck, Gertrude (Box 49, Folder 19)
  - Patient files. Perry, Hilda (Box 49, Folder 20)
  - Patient files. Pierce, Etta (Box 49, Folder 21)
  - Patient files. Proctor, Willie (Box 49, Folder 22)
  - Patient files. Pugh, Janie (Box 50, Folder 1-2)
  - Patient files. Seif, Viola Bennett (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Patient files. Shanafelt, Louise Lynn (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Patient files. Slaughter, Mae B. (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Patient files. Smith, Elizabeth (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Patient files. Stagg, Susie W. (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Patient files. Street, Mary (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Patient files. Stuart, Kate (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - Patient files. Tillotson, Frances F. (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - Patient files. Trible, Atway Drusilla (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - Patient files. Wayne, Annie G. (Box 50, Folder 12)
  - Patient files. Wilkinson, Annie Ruth (Box 50, Folder 13)
  - Patient files. Wiltshire, Emma M. (Box 50, Folder 14)
  - Room-check log for bedridden residents, May 1987-January 1988 (Box 50, Folder 15)
- VII. Other files, 1862-1981 (Box 50-52, 55-56)
  A varied collection of papers, many having to do with Confederate memorial organizations and causes. Of note are three letters, 1871 and 1880, from former C.S.A. President Jefferson Davis (1808-1889) concerning a painting he had left in the care of some Richmond friends. Also included are newspaper clippings; a small number of personal effects belonging to Elizabeth (Mrs. A.J.) Montague; a reproduction of the "Dahlgren Papers," which may have revealed a Union officer's 1864 plan to sack Richmond and execute President Davis; and the minutes book, 1911-1913, of the Richmond, Va., Lee Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy.
  - A Confederate Catechism, by Lyon Gardiner Tyler, 1930 (Box 50, Folder 16)
  - Application for admission to R.E. Lee Camp Soldiers' Home (Box 50, Folder 17)
  - Application to receive widow's pension (Box 50, Folder 18)
  - Annual reports, charters, and by-laws of various retirement homes, 1890-1908 (1 of 2) (Box 50, Folder 19)
  - Annual reports, charter, and by-laws of various retirement homes, 1890-1908 (2 of 2) (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, charter and by-laws, 1901 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Certificate of eligibility for Southern Cross of Honor (U.D.C.) (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Dahlgren Papers (reproduction) (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - Genealogical notes--Gascoigne and Moncure families (Oversize) (Box 56)
  - Genealogical notes--Lytle family (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - George E. Pickett Camp of Confederate Veterans, by-laws and rules of order, 1895 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Jefferson Davis-W.W. Davies documents, 1862-1880 (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - King and Queen County court case--Ware orphans v. Gardner executors, 1804 (Oversize) (Box 56)
  - Ladies Auxiliary, George E. Pickett Camp of Confederate Veterans, by-laws, 1896 (Box 51, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. A.J. Montague--Miscellaneous papers (Box 51, Folder 10-11)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 51, Folder 12-13)
  - Plaques for endowed rooms (Box 55)
  - Poems (Box 51, Folder 14)
  - Praise for the Home from resident Caroline Gouldin, 1909 (Box 51, Folder 15)
  - R.E. Lee Camp No. 1, Confederate Veterans, charter and by-laws, 1900 (Box 51, Folder 16)
  - Reminiscences of a Confederate Soldier of Co. C., 2nd Virginia Cavalry, by R.H. Peck (Box 51, Folder 17)
  - Robert E. Lee's General Orders No. 9 (reproduction) (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Roll, Co. E, 11th Virginia Cavalry (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - The Virginians, constitution and by-laws, member list, 1904-1906 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - United Confederate Veterans and Sons of Confederate Veterans pamphlets, 1907-1931 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy, Lee Chapter, minutes, 1911-1913 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy pamphlets, etc. (Box 52, Folder 6-7)
- VIII. Photographs and drawings, 1903-1980 and undated (Box 52-54, 56)
  Photographs and drawings of the 3 East Grace Street and 301 North Sheppard Street residences, scattered Home events, A. J. and Elizabeth Montague, and various residents, as well as a small number of photographs belonging to residents Mamie Moon and Mary Powell. Also included are several loose photographs and photograph and postcard albums belonging to C. Dunbar Roy (ca. 1874-ca. 1937), a cousin of Mrs. Montague. Roy's will left an assortment of furniture and personal effects to the Home; this may explain how these items came into the Home's collection. Drawings include a very basic plan of the Home's basement level, 1970.
  - Basic plan, basement level of Home, Nov. 1970 (Box 56)
  - Broom Drill Girls at HNCW benefit bazaar, 1903 (Box 52, Folder 8)
  - Corner of Sheppard Street and Grove Avenue, Feb. 1925 (Oversize) (Box 56)
  - C. Dunbar Roy family photos and postcards (Box 52, Folder 9-12)
  - C. Dunbar Roy family photo album (1 of 2) (Box 52, Folder 13)
  - C. Dunbar Roy family photo album (2 of 2) (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - C. Dunbar Roy family postcard album (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Photograph album, Home interior (301 N. Sheppard St.) (Box 52, Folder 14)
  - Photographs and drawings of Home exterior (301 N. Sheppard St.) (Box 52, Folder 15)
  - Photographs belonging to Mamie B. Moon (HNCW resident) (Box 53, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs belonging to Mary A. Powell (HNCW resident) (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of residents and staff at the Home, 1968 and undated (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of the Home (3 E. Grace St.) (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Photographs taken for The Washington Post, 1980 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Portrait, Olin Fisk McDowell, 59th Virginia Regiment (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Portraits, Mr. and Mrs. A.J. Montague (Oversize) (Box 56)
  - Unidentified photographs (Box 53, Folder 8)